Guide to the Montana Mercantile Company Records 1933-1939
Montana Historical Society Archives
Montana Mercantile Company Records
1933-1939
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 168
Montana Mercantile Company (Dillon, Mont.)
1 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana Mercantile Company operated a grocery store, a feed mill, and a seed and fertilizer retail outlet in Dillon, Montana. Records include general correspondence (1933-1939) and financial records.
The Montana Mercantile Company of Dillon, Montana, was incorporated by J.H. Burfeind, O.M. Best, D.T. Chapman, Leonard Eliel, M.L. Davidson, W.A. Jones, and Frank Eliel on January 4, 1893. The company was capitalized at $75,000. These men served variously as the firm's officers. In 1902 M.L. Davidson was president, W.A. Jones was vice-president, and O.M. Best served as secretary-treasurer. In 1910 W.A. Jones was president and O.M. Best secretary. The company's charter of incorporation was extended by W.A. Jones in December 1912. In 1921 Leonard and Frank Eliel, president and secretary respectively, of the Montana Mercantile Company, increased the capitalization of the firm to $150,000. The directors of the corporation at the time of the increase also included Samuel Fay Erwin as treasurer, A.I. Cashmore, and Adolph Eliel. The company's board of directors petitioned to dissolve the corporations in November 1943. During the 1930s the Montana Mercantile Company operated a grocery store, a feed mill, seed and fertilizer retail outlet, and haying operations serving ranchers, farmers, and dairymen in Dillon, Butte, and the Big Hole and Beaverhead valleys.
Content Description:
Records. 1.5 linear feet. This collection consists primarily of general correspondence (1933, 1937-1939) between the Montana Mercantile Company's president Samuel Fay Erwin and the firm's customers and wholesale suppliers reflecting everyday business matters; financial records (1936-1938); subject files (1938); miscellany; and clippings. Photographs have been transferred to the Photo Archives.
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Seed industry and trade; Wholesale trade; Land companies; Montana; Business,Industry, and Labor
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Outgoing Correspondence
  - Circular letter re alfalfa hay sales (includes names of dairymen), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- General Correspondence
  - A (correspondents include G.W. Allen and Sons; Associated Merchants of Montana), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - H-L (correspondents include H.L. Hammond; Carl H. Hartwig; Frank W. Haskins; M.E. Hay; Clarence O. Hay; Heflin and Company; T.E. Hegna Grain Company; W.P. Hendrix; F.E. Herr; J.G. Hodges; Marie Holenstein; V.A. Hutchings; Idaho Falls Warehouse Company; Industrial Accident Board; Independent Mines; Individual Service Company; Interstate Feed Company; William L. Irvine; Howard Jones; R.W. Jones; Maurice Keating; John Kent; Kessler Brewing Company; Keystone Rubber Company, Inc.; Charles A. Krause Milling Company; Lakeview Mercantile Company; Lakner Brothers; Mrs. George Lasich; R.A. Lasich), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - M (correspondents include Hans Madsen; Magazine of Wall Street; James N. Mansfield; Ed Marchesseau, Sr.; Martin Markovich; Fred Martin; Tom McAdam; McAllister Feed Company; F.B. McGregor; Clyde McKee; Victor McKerlee; M.D. McVay; Megeath Coal Company; George M. Melton; L.A. Metzel; Midland Implement Company, Inc.; Midwest Grain Company; Hans Mikkelson; Miller Brothers Company; Fred M. Mills; Missoula Brewing Company; Missoula Mercantile Company; Sam Mochen; John Molignoni; Joseph Monaghan; Monida Mercantile Company; Monroe Dairy; Montana Distributors, Inc.; Montana Civil Liberties Association; Montana Hardware Company; Montana Power Company; Dan Mooney; Mountain Valley Seed Company), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Mrs. Dissolina Martini (re Silver Bow Dairy, Butte), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Montana Flour Mills Company, 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - N (correspondents include Nay Brothers; Theodore Nelson; Nettick and Sons; New England Mills Company; The New Husler Flour Mills; New York Life Insurance Company; Northrup, King and Company), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Sterling H. Nelson Company, 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - O-P (correspondents include Occidental Seed Company; Ofreddi and Forcella; Opal Mercantile Company; Pecos Valley Alfalfa Growers Association; Henry Pedretti; Planters Cotton Oil Company; Pocatello Mill and Elevator), 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - B-M (correspondents include Chicago Milwaukee St. Paul and Pacific R.R. Company; Continental Oil Company; Dell Service Station; Elliott Seed Company; Montana State College; J.E. Gallaway), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - A (correspondents include John G. Albers; W.E. Allen; Amberg File and Index Company; American Can Company; Tom E. Ames; Ralph J. Anderson; H.S. Armitage; Associated Merchants of Montana; Atwood-Larson Company), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Anaconda Sales Company, Fertilizer Department, 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - F.C. Ayres Milling and Grain Company, 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - B-D (correspondents include Baldwin and Jones Feed Company; Bank of America; Barkemeyer Seed Company; Basin Montana Tunnel Company; Beaverhead County High School; Taylor Bradley; Butte Neon Outdoor Advertising Company; Canadian Bank of Commerce; C.L. Coconougher; Louis S. Cohn Company; William R. Davis Agency; W.C. Dorsett Company; Dun and Bradstreet, Inc.), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Elliott Seed Company, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - E (correspondents include Lambert Eliel; El Monte Hay Market, Inc.; Frank G. Ely; Emerson Electric Manufacturing Company; J.H. Enright), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - F (correspondents include Farmers Mercantile Elevator Company; Federal Hardware and Implement Mutuals; The Federal Land Bank of Spokane; Ferry-Morse Seed Company; First National Bank of Twin Bridges; Flanley Grain Company; A.H. French), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Q-W (correspondents include Paul T. Quick; Tarr and McComb Grain Company, Ltd.; Thomas Brothers; George L. Tracy Company; United Steel and Wire Company; Utah-Idaho Grain Company; Ucon Cooperative Mill, Inc.; United States Treasury; Warrer Arthur Grain; Wason Brothers Company; Edwin Whitworth; Clarence E. Wohl), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
- Financial Records
  - Inventories, 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Tax receipts, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
- Photographs and Printed Materials
  - Lists of photographs and printed materials transferred to the Photo Archives and Library respectively, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
- Subject Files
  - R.J. Dansie promissory note collection, 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - United States government contracts, 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
- Miscellany
  - United States government agricultural bulletins, 1933, 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Tax Research Institute materials, 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1938, n.d. (Box-folder 2 / 8)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous ( re Butte School faculty; crested wheatgrass; national debt; insect control campaign), dates vary (Box-folder 2 / 9)